so this is from the sugar note on humma
in the second paragraph the question of
comma or action what should I do is the
ethical question for all personal action
all action done by me is either acocella
or couselor unn still for skillful
skillful action is rooted in Loba dosa
moja or lust ate delusion and apart from
resulting in future of dukkha and um
pleasure leads to the arising of action
not to the cessation of action skillful
action is rooted in non lust non hate
and non delusion and me it's a cessation
of action not to the arising of action
the patina does not understand this to
deceive neither the arising nor
cessation of action the duty some Pune
does understand this Cindy sees both the
rising and cessation of action the our
Honda understands this but has also
reached the cessation of action since
for him the question what should I do
no more arises to the extent they are
still in tension in the case of they are
not there is still conscious action but
since it is neither unskillful nor
skillful it no long is no longer the
action in the ethical sense extinction
Nirvana is the cessation of ethics so
what interested me with with this was
idea of things leading to more action
for less action and that's kind of what
the petitioner needs to understand it's
a matter than I guess of how it is one
what is the distinction between those
two like what what is it then
between greed hatred delusion non-green
900 non delusion that does lead to this
cessation of of action like what is what
is that what is what is special
different between them right before like
one thing to point that point out is the
problem with with petitioner and the
notion of action is that they cannot see
the negative aspect of a positive action
they cannot see D so let's let's say
action a is done then you replace that
by doing something else as in you do an
action B then you replace that by doing
something else but the direction see
what petitioner needs to start
discerning is that you don't replace
action a with action B you want to be
able to develop a non action of not a as
in absence of action a and that's the
definition of sila and virtue being done
rightly in the beginning people take on
the preset and they do them even if
you're not actively doing anything your
attitude is of doing it keeping it but
if you have been developed in virtue
correctly then those presets start
keeping you so to speak in other words
you recognize and it's not about doing
sila it's more about not doing non sila
not doing non virtually and and the
reason that's why the sila is a
necessary precondition for any
understanding is because it emulates the
principle the principle of overcoming
the unwholesome so initially of course a
petitioner just needs to abstain from
our Olsen abstain from our wholesome action
Olsen abstain from our wholesome action
speech and thought but that's only there
to create a basis for understanding and
that understanding is when you see the
negative aspect as in the peripheral
them the general at the general nature
of the unwholesome and you stop
entertaining the unwholesome and the
general nature becomes apparent when you
realize that unwholesome is concerned
with the content of your thought not the
presence of that content of the thought
so in that manner you can cultivate non
unwholesome which is automatically also
so you're saying then that the wrong
thing to do is kind of trying to make
yourself wholesome so to speak by doing
good ethical things that people agree
yeah is nothing wrong with it - is
nothing unwholesome to do that but it's
wrong to think that that's the way of
leading you out to Folsom and
unwholesome you get out of it by not
engaging with unwholesome and then
discerning that absence of unwholesome
peace was wholesome is ultimately
wholesome in the sense that pertains to
the freedom from both wholesome and
unwholesome but when you recognize that
you don't need to do something all you
need to do is avoid doing certain things
as in avoid the unwholesome that in
itself is wholesome so it's a negative
action in that sense which means you
can't really call it an action
abstaining abstaining from unwholesome
action if done rightly it's not an
action
so is that is that how it is then when
he says the our hon you know he Aviance
obviously still do things you know just
become rocks or blocks of wood yeah but
there's there's no action there and
exactly we're speaking because action
was on the level of that assumption of
doing either doing good to doing bad
that is fueled by greed averse delusion
is filled by desire let's feel by
craving even for wholesome like crazy
even for wholesome it that's why
sometimes people I because I'm not free
from desire I won't do anything
wholesome but that's a mistake you have
no choice but to do whatever you do out
of a desire are you you you keep doing
good then on account of avoiding bad
because then on account of doing good
you can see the abstaining from doing
both bad and now this good is that
negative phenomena behind the action
that you can discern so yeah if say
being immoral is a being moral is B so
you then do B but it's still done as an
action but then on top of it if you want
to go beyond and you can go on the
beyond of being being moral you can then
use that action to understand the nature
of action to transcend the content of
action as I was describing in the
previous video so if you have stopped
doing done awesome and now your act is
purely virtuous kept by the precepts in
the danger in the slightest fault your
action is action B there is a good
action and then on top of that you start
then discerning okay so I don't need to
go into action C now no do I need to
revert to action a all I can do now is
look at the nature behind the action B
which in itself it's not B and then you
can stop doing that as well that's why
like a sotapanna he lets go of sila
butter para mas he lets go of the or the
virtue and beauty I must be doing this
as somebody who practices that doesn't
mean he becomes immoral he just means he
stops doing it on the level of action
and starts developing it on the level of
mind that's why a sake sake
disciple sort of honor hi all he needs
to do is keep his virtue unblemished and
it will result in our country it will
result in in freedom freedom from the
most freedom from the most results and
happiness happiness joy and tranquility
tranquility and then clear seeing and
understanding but you can't just keep
the preset and then expect to end in the
as a result have as a result the
understanding of Dhamma you need to keep
the precepts to create that basis of
good action and then on the basis of
good wholesome action you have to see
the nature of action which in itself
it's not that content of action that you
are doing so abstaining from doing
something there's no need to become an
action if you can develop it in that
manner
obviously people always have some sense
of you know what is right and what is
wrong regardless of whether they ever
really read anything about ethics or
morality or anything like that and a lot
of people you know they say that the
Buddha and all the other religious
people leaders taught the same morality
same ethics like in the Ten Commandments
and other such things like thou shalt
not kill not steal clothes you know
basic precepts so what is it about the
Buddha's exhortation about these things
that differentiates them from any other
person talking about what is good what
is bad well in layman's terms the
difference is that the Buddha tells you
to do good so that eventually for
understanding you can abandon both good
and bad all the other religions pretty
much tell you you do good so you get
even better as in you get reborn in
heaven or you get more of a reward from
green dudes and Christianity
all the other religions so that's the
difference the Buddha doesn't just tell
you to replace bad action with good
action and be rewarded for it he tells
action and then understand it fully that
would then truly free you because you
might be rewarded for your good action
but the other reward will expire the
more last forever
and then you're back in square one or
even worse but the Buddha frees you from
the bondage of action the bondage of
having to choose the bondage of having
to act and intended some other people
especially the non-religious can have
the view that there is there is no
morality like it's me it's like a
nihilistic view it's all relative that
ethics and morals just come from you
know the laws of society and different
cultures but when we when we read this
it seems pretty clear like like you know
killing is unwholesome
whatever the reasons the motivation is
always unwholesome existential
discrepancy is unwholesome and it's it's
it's it's felt as wrong by anyone no
matter of their background culture views
politics religion and that's what that's
what every everything that's considered
bad contains that discrepancy as in true
life you deny life or someone else's
life which is not yours to deny with
poor lying again taking that which is
not yours which is not meant for you
stealing cheating harming again all of
that course that discrepancy people feel
that that there is that like you the
universal morality that can be discerned
on the basis of nature of things now
people can debate about the specifics of
it but overall everybody knows deep down
where the direction is motivated in
overriding the discrepancy in creating
and acting out of greed aversion to lose
hatred and so sometimes when it comes to
thinking about what's good and bad
people especially philosophical in mind
I'd like to start you know pose it
positing all these theoretical problems
like the flow statement by the the
trolley problem for example what kind of
playing devil's advocate felt like you
know killing is okay if it's let's say
someone's a chronic disease and you know
you're relieving them pain and suffering
so there's there any value and kind of
thinking of these kind of complicated
ethical questions or is it just a
reaction all of them it's a distraction
for somebody want to practice AMA but
even if you if you want to think about
them for whatever reason all the
conclusions there those theoretical
questions would arrive at are based on
assuming the external point of view of
yourself and then making the universal
sort of decision which which is
impossible it's inconceivable you can't
imagine the experience outside of your
experience as a whole which means you
always abound with your point of view
which means killing is always bad no
amount of external reasoning and the
environment can justify it
so if they say well if I don't kill this
person he'll kill 100 well killing
hundred debts on him that's something
you so then what you really say is oh
I'll kill him so he doesn't do anything
bad in his life so I'll do something bad
so he doesn't do anything bad which
means somebody will need to take
responsibility for that killing and
skilling is always bad so when it comes
to discerning all seven holes and then
it seems like the most important thing
is personal responsibility
absolutely it's not it's a necessary
thing yeah and that's what I mean
through that personal responsibility
you can obviously abstain from doing
unwholesome and into accepting
responsibility for wholesome you can
start seeing the the nature of action in
regard to it as in the necessity of the
point of view the necessity of
intentionality but the non necessity of
appropriation of direction you cannot
see that in unwholesome action because
by default it's already perverted based
on that discrepancy of appropriation but
also action isn't that doesn't mean that
wholesome action is understood so that's
what I mean you use you abstain from
doing good through doing good but then
disowning the ownership of that while
you're doing it so then it becomes non
doing then you don't really have to do
it
oh so so just to add more to that whole
to the whole thing of ownership through
doing wholesome action ones motivation
can be revealed and if the motivation
itself does not contain that discrepancy
that perversion of of the distension
discrepancy whether through killing
lying stealing acting out of greed
aversion delusion then it can be seen
the extent of one responsibility to that
to that wholesome action that a person
does as in intentionality in itself
arises on its own but you choosing to
act upon certain intentions on account
of in oaring other intentions that's on
you and that's something that gets
obscured through the habitual action
virtual action of unwholesome nature you
cannot see this background of
intentionality behind and if you are
proved the unwholesome intentions that's
when you stop acting in that sense there
can also be the temptation just talking
about the cessation of action and a
person just tries to just do as little
as they can
yes failing to see that that direction
at the time it's a common boils down to
what in the essential philosophy they
were saying but you are free to choose
but at the same time you cannot not
choose which means you condemned to be
free to not to be free and condemned to
choice because if you say okay I'm not
going to choose anything you chose that
that's the definition of Karma that the
Buddha described is action you cannot
help but do something so the only way to
stop truly doing anything at choosing is
to understand the nature of their choice
the nature of intention ality inherent
in it that has nothing to do with you
and then the degree of your
responsibility that you then add to it
by choosing this by intending this on
account of that choice is an intentional
intention but intention itself it's not
you're doing and does not need to be
appropriated not knowing that people
appropriated and then by default and
then you intentionally intend further
your own intentions it's just I am doing
this and that does become your action
but if you recognize that intention
ality is bound with things with the five
aggregates with experience as a whole
then you can stop entertaining the
unwholesome habits of that
intentionality and then stop
entertaining the wholesome ones the ones
they do not contain that discrepancy of
existential nature and that's the
definition of Kosala is Kosala in a
fuselage aku so